The Life Of Muhammadﷺ, Madinan Period, Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
اَلسَّلَامُ عَلَيْكُمْ وَرَحْمةُ الله وَبَرَكَاتُه’
We're finishing with some miscellaneous events concerning Fath e Makkah(فتح مكه),
In Sha Allah O Ta'ala (اِنْ شاءالله تعالى).
Rasool Allah ﷺ, when he entered into Makkah he chose a Mo'azzin(مؤذن), someone to call the Adhan(آذان).
And the particular choice of Rasool Allah ﷺ was Bilal Ibn Rabah رضي الله عنه.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ had Bilal(بلال) climb over Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) to deliver the Adhan(آذان).
According to Younas Bin Mukhair(يونس بن مخير), Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered
اَمَرَبِلَالً اَنْ يُؤَذَنَ لِيَغِيْظَ بِهِ الْمُشْرِكِيْنْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered Bilal(بلال) to give Adhan(آذان) in order to anger the polytheists.
Because Bilal(بلال) was seen as a slave,
and now he's calling to the Salah(صلاة), and he's climbing over Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) to do it.
And therefore there were some narrations of comments made by the people of Makkah
showing their displeasure with the fact that Bilal(بلال) was the one, who is calling the Adhan(آذان),
like one of them said; Can you see this black crow barking from on top of Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه)
and things like that derogatory terms made by the Mushrikeen(مشركين) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ, intended to have Bilal(بلال) make the Adhan(آذان) to show them
just what we were talking about before, the new era that Islam is bringing,
where class and caste of Jahilliyah(جاهلية) do not matter anymore
and it is Taqwa(تقوى) that makes a person high or low.
It is according to how close they are to Allahعَزّوجَلّ, it is their Taqwa(تقوى) it is their following of Islam.
And according to Saeed Bin Musayyib رحمه الله,
that particular day when the people entered into Makkah
it wasn't a day of celebration, it wasn't a day of partying.
It says;
فَلَمَّا كَانَ لَيْلَةْ دَخَلَ النَّاسِ مَكَّه، لَيْلَةَ الْفَتْحْ
لَمْ يَزالُ فِيْ تَكْبِيْرٍ، وَ فِيْ تَهْلِيْلٍ ، وَ فِيْ طَوَافٍ بِالْبَيْتْ حَتَّى اَصْبَح
فَقَالَ اَبُوْ سٌفِيَّانْ لِهِنْدْ اَتَرَيْنَ هَذَا مِنَّ الله ، قَالَ : نَعْمْ ، هَذا مِنَّ الله
When the people entered into Makkah, the day of conquest,
they remained in Takbeer(تكبير) and Tahleel(تحليل).
Tahleel(تحليل) meaning saying;
لَا اِلَهَ اِلَّا الله
And Takbeer(تكبير) means saying Allah-Ho-Akbar(الله اكبر)
and Tawaf Bil Bait(طواف بِالْبَيت) circling Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
They've been away from Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) for a long time.
And now they are pleased and happy that Allahعَزّوجَلّ allowed them to enter into Makkah and to worship Allah
according to the rules of Islam, while Islam is dominant in Makkah.
So, they were making Tawaf(طواف) around the house all the way until, the morning there was Ibadah(عبادة), all night
all night long, there was Ibadah(عبادة).
Wherever you go in Makkah you can see people making Takbeer(تكبير) and making Tahleel(تحليل)
and making Tawaf(طواف) around the house of Allah.
So, Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) went back to his wife and said;
Do you think this is from Allah?
I mean, it's an impressive scene, it's something that even affected these people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) people of Makkah,
who are just moments ago Kuffar(كفار).
So Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) told his wife:
اَتَرَيْنَ هَذَا مِنَّ الله
Do you think this is from Allah?
She said: Yes, this is from Allah.
And then Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) met Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
You told Hind(هند): Do you think this is from Allah?
And Hind told you: Yes, I think this is from Allah.
Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) said;
I testify that you are the Messenger of Allah.
No one overheard our conversation, there was no one there but we, me and Hind(هند).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said as narrated by Al-Bukhari(اَلْبُخَارِيْ);
إنَّ الله حَرَّمَ مَكَّةَ يَومَ خَلَقَ السَّمَوَاتِ والأرْضَ
فَهِيَّ حَرَامٌ بِحَرَمَ اللَّهِ إلى يَومُ الْقِيَامَةِ، لَا تَحِلُّ لِأحَدٍ قَبْلِي
وَلَا تَحِلُّ لِاَحَدٍ بَعْدِيْ ، وَلَمْ تَحْلُلْ لِيْ إلَّا سَاعَةً مِنَّ الدَّهَر
لَا يُنَفَّرُ صَيْدُهَا، وَلَا يُعْضَدُ شَوْكُهَا، ولَا يُخْتَلَى خَلَاهَا، ولَا تَحِلُّ لُقَطَتُهَا، إلَّا لِمُنْشِطْ
Allah has made Makkah as a sanctuary, the day He created the heavens and the earth
it is the sanctuary by Allah's having made it so,
and will remain such until, the Judgment Day.
Conflict in it was not made permissible for anyone before myself, nor for anyone after me.
And this only for a short time.
In it, gain may not be hunted, it's trees may not be cut down, nor mates vegetation be uprooted
and items found in it, belong to the Finder only after announcement of the Find.
Al-Abbas bin Abdul Muttalib رضي الله عنه want to exclude from this rule a plant called Al-Izkhar(ألإذخر).
Because Rasool Allah ﷺ said: You're not allowed to cut down trees.
So, Al-Abbas(العباس) wanted to exclude the Al-Izkhar(ألإذخر) .
Because they use it for the dead, it's a fragrant tree, it has a nice smell to it.
And apparently it's also used as fuel for blacksmiths
because in another narration says; Lil-Qaim(لِلْقَيْمْ).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said except for Al-Izkhar(ألإذخر).
Rasool Allah ﷺ allowed them to cut down this particular plant or a tree but nothing else.
So, Makkah and also Madina are Haram(حرام) and they are a sanctuary,
and hunting is not allowed there in and uprooting trees is not allowed.
There's a Hadith(حديث) by Abu Hurairah رضي الله عنه, we go through it In Sha Allah(اِنْ شَاالله).
Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) says, that
delegations went to meet Muawiya(معاويه), so we're talking about a long time after the Fath(فتح) of Makkah(مكه).
We're talking about in the time, when Muawiya(معاويه) was a Khalifah(خليفه)
وَذَالِكَ فِي رَمَضَانْ and that was during the time of Ramadan(رمضان).
فَكَانَ يَصْنَعُ بْعْضُنَا لِبَعْضِ الطَّعَامْ
So, we would prepare food for each other.
And this shows you the social aspect of the, life of the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم and Tabieen(تابعين)
these were delegations that were there.
And rather than everybody having their meal alone, they would invite each other.
So, Abu Hurairah(ابو هريره) said; I invite you to my place.
Now, Abu Hurairah(ابو هريره) it says in this narration.
مِمَّا يُكْثِرْ اَنْ يَدْعُوْنَا الى رَحْلِهْ
He was the most who would invite us, he would invite us the most.
So, one of At-Tabieen(تابعين), wanted to invite Abu Hurairah رضي الله عنه,
so he said;
فَقُلْتُ اَلَا اَصْنَعَ طَعَامً فَاَدْعُوْهُمْ اِلَى رَحْلِيْ
So I decided that I'm going to invite them to my place this time.
Obviously, these are not permanent dwellings, they are all visitors.
فَاَمِرْتُ بِطَعَامٍ يَصْنَعْ، ثُمَّ لَقِيْتُ اَبَا هُرَيْرَةْ
I prepared the food and then I met Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره)
and I told him;
اَلدَّعْوَةْ عِنْدِيْ اَلْلَيْلَةْ
Invitation is at my place tonight.
He said;
اَسْبَقْتَنِيْ
He said: you beat me to it.
I said: Yes.
So, Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره), when he arrived at the gathering,
he wanted to make it a beneficial gathering. So, he said;
اَلَا اعْلِمَكُمْ بِحَدِيْثٍ مِنْ حَدِيْثِكُمْ، يَا مَعْشَرِالْاَنْصَارْ؟
Shouldn't I tell you a Hadith(حديث) that belongs to you, O people of Al-Ansaar(اَلْاَنْصَار)
apparently most of these people who were there, were from Al-Ansaar(اَلْاَنْصَار).
ثُمَّ ذَكَرَ فَتَحْ مَكَّةْ فَقَالْ
So, he talked about the story of the conquest of Makkah.
He said, when Rasool Allah ﷺ came to Makkah he sent Az-Zubair(ألزبير) on one of the two wings of the army,
and he sent Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) commanding the other wing
and Abu Obaidah(ابوعبيدة) was commanding the foot soldiers.
So, they entered into Makkah and Rasool Allah ﷺ, was in his battalion.
So, he saw me and he said: O Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) I told him;
لَبَّيْكَ يَا رَسُوْل الله
So, he said: No one but the Ansaar(أنْصَار) should come to me.
So, this was a private gathering that Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to have with Al-Ansaar(ألْأنْصَار).
So, Abu Hurairah(ابوهريره) went and invited the Ansaar(أنْصَار), he called them,
so they came and surrounded Rasool Allah ﷺ from every direction.
قُرَيْشْ وَبَشَتَ لَهَا اَوْبَاشًا
Quraish(قريش) has mobilize the force of some men.
And these were people from the outskirts of Makkah to fight,
but they didn't risk themselves going into the fight.
Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they mobilize this force but they themselves did not join and they said;
If they win then we will join if they lose then we're safe.
And you can't win in this way.
If you don't want to participate yourself,
if you don't want to be in the front line like Rasool Allah ﷺ, like the Sahabah(صحابه) were there's no hope of winning.
So, those who are hiding and sending their foot soldiers to do all the work,
while they are cowering behind and hiding, they will not win.
So these Aobaash(أوباش) these people who are supposed to fight for Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), they were defeated.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَتَرَوْنَ اِلَى اَوْبَاشٍ قُرَيْش وَاَتْبَاعِهِمْ؟ ثُمَّ قَالَ بِيَدَيْهِ اِحَدَاهُمَا عَلَى اُخْرَى، ثُمَّ قَالَ حَتَّى تُوَافُوْنِيْ بِالصَّفَا
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ gave his orders to fight these Aobaash(أوباش)
and many of them were killed and then the fighting stopped.
Anyway, they ended up meeting on As-Safah(اَلصَّفاء).
And when they met with Rasool Allah ﷺ, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مَنْ دَخَلَ دَارْ اَبِيْ سُفِيَان فَهُوَ آمِنْ
whoever, enters into the house of Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان), he is safe.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has announced that whoever enters into the house of Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) is safe.
Now the house of Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) is not gonna be enough for all of the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), obviously
but Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to give Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) this honor to draw him closer to Islam.
But he also said:
وَمَنْ دَخَلَ مَنْزِلَه’ فَهُوَ آمِنْ
Whoever enters into his house, he will be safe, so no one will attack you in your house.
But if we see you on the streets then you will be killed.
So, it's like a curfew, nobody is allowed to leave their homes.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ after this conflict happened,
the Ansaar رضي الله عنهم, they felt that Rasool Allah ﷺ now because he's back in his hometown, he might leave them and stay behind.
Now, he's with his clan, he's with his relatives he's in Makkah.
So, he's going to leave us that's the end.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ called them and said;
أقُلْتُمْ اَمَّا رَجُلْ فَاَدْكْتُه’ رَغْبَةَ فِيْ قَرْيَتِه ، قَالُوْ قَدْكَانَ ذَالِكْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them: Did you say so? They said: Yes.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them;
اِنِّيْ عَبْدُالله وَرَسُوْلُه
I am the servant of Allah and His messenger.
هَاجَرْتُ اِلَى الله وَاِلَيْكُمْ
I made Hijrah(هجرة) to Allah and to you.
فَالْمَحْيَا مَحْيَاكُمْ وَالْمَمَاتُ مَمَاتُكُمْ
Life is with you, and death is with you.
فَاَقْبَلُوا الَيْه يَبْكُوْنَ
So, they came crying to Rasool Allah ﷺ, and they said;
وَلله مَا قُلْنَا اَلَّذِيْ قُلْنَا اِلَّا الظنْ بِالله وَرَسُوْلِه
We only said, what we said because of our eagerness and desire to have you with us
and our love of Allah and love of His messenger.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اِنَّ الله وَرَسُوْلَه يَصَدِّقَانِكُمْ
Allah and His Messenger believe you.
Safwaan Ibn Umayyah(صفوان إبن أمية) was one of the leaders of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) he fled
because he thought, he has done so much against Islam and Rasool Allah ﷺ would kill him.
Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب), his close friend in Jahilliyah(جاهلية)
and if you remember, we talked about Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب).
Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) is the man whom Safwaan(صفوان) sent to assassinate Rasool Allah ﷺ
and when he arrived in Madina, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him about his plan to come and assassinate him.
So, he was shocked that Rasool Allah ﷺ knew the details of this plan and he ended up becoming Muslim.
So, now Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) when he heard about Safwaan(صفوان) running away he followed him.
Safwaan(صفوان) went to Jeddah to ride a boat and go to Yemen.
So, Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) told him; I have come to you from Rasool Allah ﷺ
because Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) spoke to Rasool Ullah and said;
O Messenger of Allah Safwaan(صفوان) is the leader of his people give him immunity.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said: I will give him immunity.
Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب) said give me a sign, a token.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ gave him his turban,
as a sign of the fact that Rasool Allah ﷺ is giving Safwaan(صفوان) immunity.
Umair(عمير) took the turban of Rasool Ullah and he went to meet Safwaan(صفوان).
Safwaan(صفوان) told him; Stay away from me.
Umair(عمير) said; I have come to you from the Most Merciful and from the most compassionate man, and the most forgiving
and his kingdom is yours and this position is yours and his honor is yours.
He's telling him that he's your relative
and whatever good happens to Rasool Ullah is good that is happening to you.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ has given you immunity.
He said: You're lying to me.
he said: This is a sign this is the turban of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Safwaan(صفوان) came back with Umair Ibn Wahb(عمير إبن وهب)
and he went to Rasool Allah ﷺ, and said;
This man is claiming that you forgive me and give me immunity Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Yes.
Safwaan(صفوان) said: Give me two months to think about it, before becoming Muslim.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: I give you four months.
Safwaan(صفوان) eventually became Muslim.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has destroyed the idols and the Kuffr(كفر) of Makkah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted to spread the sovereignty of Islam in the surrounding area.
So he sent Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) in Ramadan(رمضان) to Banni Judaimah(بني جذيمة),
this is an Arab tribe close to Makkah.
It says in Bukhari(بخاريْ), Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) to Banni Judaimah(بني جذيمة).
فَدَعَاهُمْ اِلَى الْاِسْلَامْ
He invited them to Islam,
فَلَمْ يُحْسِنُو اَنْ يَقُوْلُوْ اَسْلَمْنَا
They were not educated enough to say we become Muslim but they said;
صَبَاعْنَا
The Kuffar(كفار) of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) when somebody would become Muslim
they would say, he has become a Sa'bay(صابع).
Sa'bay(صابع) is one of the religions of Jahilliyah(جاهلية)
and it was a derogatory term against anyone, who would become Muslim.
So, they would never say that such and such has become Muslim.
They would say such and such Saba'a(صباع).
Now, Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) he told them become Muslim, they said: Saba'ana(صباعنا)
In reality, they wanted to be Muslim, but they will not learned enough to know that they should use the term Aslamna(أسلمنا).
They picked up this word that they heard everybody else say and they were repeating it.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) killed them.
And he captured the rest
and he handed over one prisoner to every soldier of his army.
And then Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) gave his instructions to the army
every soldier to execute his prisoner.
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) was in this army and he said;
In the name of Allah, I'm not going to kill my prisoner.
وَلله لَا اَقْتُلْ اَسِيْرِيْ ،وَلَا يَقْتُلْ رَجُلٌ مِنْ اَصْحَابِي اَسِيْرًا
I'm not going to kill my prisoner and none of my companions are going to kill their's.
Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) saw that there's this was a clear mistake, on behalf of Khalid(خالد).
These people have become Muslim and then they were killed, and then they were taken as prisoners.
And now we are told to execute our prisoners, I am not going to do it.
So, it was a clear disobeying of the order of the Ameer(امير) on behalf of Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر).
Now Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) knows the teachings of Islam that you should obey the Umarah(أمراء), follow the Ameer(أمير)
but he also knows that we should only follow the Ameer(أمير), when the Ameer(أمير) gives us an order that is Halal(حلال).
If he tells us to do something that is Haram(حرام) there is no obedience.
And we know an army is that such a thing mutiny is such a dangerous thing to do.
But Abdullah Ibn Umar رضي الله عنه not only did it himself
but he said also all of my companions people, who will listen to me,
the people who came with me, they're not going to kill their prisoners.
So, the issue was raised with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) that what you have done is right.
Rasool Allah ﷺ approved Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) in his disobedience to the Ameer(أمير).
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ raised his hands and said;
اَللَّهُمَ اِنِيْ اَبْرَاءُ اِلَيْكَ مِمَّا صَنْعَ خَالِدْ اَللَّهُمَ اِنِيْ اَبْرَاءُ اِلَيْكَ مِمَّا صَنْعَ خَالِدْ
O Allah, I declare that I am free of what Khalid(خالد) has done.
O Allah I declare that I'm innocent of what Khalid(خالد) has done.
Rasool Allah ﷺ made it clear that what Khalid(خالد) has done is wrong.
These people should not have been killed.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ approved, Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) in his action.
So the first lesson we learn here is that we should not follow Aulea Al Amoor(أولياء الأمور), Walli Ul Amr(ولي الأمر) the people in authority,
when they tell us to do something Haram(حرام).
They are to be disobeyed, if they tell us to do something Haram(حرام).
Another incident that happened with this Sariyyah(سريه),
there was a man among them who didn't really belong to that tribe.
But he was there because the woman whom he loves is from that tribe.
So, that's the only reason why he was there.
He was among the people, who were arrested and his hands were tied.
So he told the Muslim soldier, who was guarding him
to just allow me to go and speak, he pointed out towards some women
and he told the Muslim just allow me to go and
have a final visit or final word with those women over there and then do with me whatever you want, just the last sight.
So, the Muslim allowed him, so he went and he said;
اَسْلمِيْ حُبَيْشْ ، قَبْلَنَا نَفَادَ الْعَيْشْ
Aslami(أسلمي) means accept or means become Muslim
Hubeesh(حُبيش), her name.
قَبْلَنَا نَفَادَ الْعَيْشْ
Before life is over.
She said:
فَدَيْتُكَ
I would sacrifice myself for you.
And then he was taken and executed.
She saw that and she came over him and sight once or twice
and then she fell next to him dead.
When this story was related to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَمَا كَانَ فِيْكُمْ رَجُلٌ رَحِيْمْ
Wasn't there a merciful man among you.
Not only was the killing wrong but also you killed this man in such a way
and Rasool Allah ﷺ felt sorry for these people and what happened to them
and therefore Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Ali Ibn Abi Talib رضي الله عنه to pay the Diya(دية).
So, Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) was sent by Rasool Allah ﷺ to pay Blood Money, compensation for all those who were killed.
Because the ones, who were killed are Muslims
they made a mistake by saying Saba'ana(صباعنا) but in reality what they mean is Aslam'na(أسلمنا).
They were paid for everything.
Anything that was missing, their belongings that were taken Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب) compensated them for everything
blood money in addition to any belongings that were taken from them.
And then there was some leftover money with him, he gave it to them just in case.
So, this is how Rasool Allah ﷺ dealt with this situation.
These were Muslims, who are killed by mistake.
They were paid blood money, but pay attention to what Ibn Kathir(ابن كثير) has to say after he mentions this incident.
He said;
فَقَتَلَ طَائِفَةْ كَثِيْرَةْ مِنْهُمْ، وَقَتَلَ اَكْثَرَ الْاَسرَى اَيْضاً
Ibn Kathir(ابن كثير) say;
فقتلا,
He killed, meaning Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد),
he killed many of them and he killed most of the prisoners also.
وَمَعَ هَذَا لَمْ يَعْزِلَه’ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
Nevertheless, Rasool Allah ﷺ did not fire him from his position.
بَلِّ اسْتَمَرَّ بِهِ اَمِيْرًا
But Rasool Allah ﷺ kept on appointing Khalid(خالد) in positions of responsibility as an Ameer(امير).
وَاِنْ كَانَ تَبرا مِنْه’ فِيْ صَنْيِعْهِ ذَالِكْ
Even though Rasool Allah ﷺ announced and declared that he is free and innocent of what Khalid(خالد) has done.
وَوَدَى مَا كَانَ جَنَاه’ خَطَاً فِيْ دَمِّ اَوْ مَالٍ
And Rasool Allah ﷺ paid compensation for the mistakes of Khalid(خالد) that were done in blood or wealth.
فَفِيْهِ دَلِيْلٌ لَاَحَدٍ الْقَوْلَيْنِ بَيْنَ الْعَلَمَاءْ
In this there's evidence for one of the opinion of the scholars.
فِيْ اَنَّ خَطَاَ الْاِمَامْ يَكُوْن فِيْ بَيْتِ الْمَال’
That when the Imam(اِمَام) commits a mistake
the money is not paid from his money but from the treasury of the Muslims, Wallah O Alam(والله اعلم).
And then he says:
وَلِهَذا لَمْ يَعْزِلْه’ اَلصَدِّيق حِيْنَ قَتَلَ مَالِك بِنْ نُوْيْرَةْ اَيَّامً الرِّدَّةْ،
وَتَاَّوَل عَلَيْهِ مَا تَاَّوَّلَ حِيْنَ ضَرَبَ عُنُقَه’ وَاصْطَفى اِمْرَاَتَه’ اُمُ تَمِيْمْ
And that is why Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه did not change him, did not fire him, in the time of riddah(ردة) during the days of Apostasy
and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) excused him, when he killed Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويره), who was supposedly Muslim.
And he took over his wife Umm O Tamim(أم تميم).
And we talked about this in the lecture series of Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
that Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) killed Malik Bin Nuwairah(مالك بن نويره)
and then he took his wife Umm O Tamim(أم تميم).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) was angry by the actions of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) and said;
اِعْزِلْه’ فَاِنَّ فِيْ سَيْفِه رَهَقاً
Fire him, change him because his sword is severe.
فَقَالَ اَلصِدِيِقْ لَا اَغْمِدُ سَيْفَاً سَلَّهُ الله عَلَى الْمُشْرِكِيْنَ
I am not gonna sheath a sword that was unsheathed by Allahعَزّوجَلّ on the Mushrikeen(مشركين), on the polytheists.
This was a sword drawn by Allahعَزّوجَلّ on the Kuffar(كفار), I'm not gonna put it down.
Therefore we can learn from this Hadd-El-Nabwi(ألحدّ النبوي), the Sunnah(سنة) in dealing with the mistakes of the Muslims in battle.
These were Muslims and they were compensated
They were Muslim and they were compensated for the mistake of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد)
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) was not imprisoned.
He was not fired from his position.
Why Because there is Ta'aweel(تعويل).
He didn't assume them to be Muslim.
But if a leader kills Muslims and he knows that they are Muslim then this is a different situation.
Here the Hukm(حكم) would be different.
The situation we're talking about
is where the issue was clear to people like Abdullah Ibn Umar(عبدالله ابن عمر) and the ones with him that these are Muslim.
But with Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), he definitely did not consider them to be Muslim.
I mean, we cannot assume no one should assume that Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) ordered Muslims to be executed.
That is impossible! That's not the case.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) considered them to be Kuffar(كفار).
A Muslim is never handed over to the Kuffar(كفار) and the Muslim is never betrayed
because Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
اَلْمُسْلِمْ أَخُ الْمُسْلِمْ، لَا يَظْلِمُه، وَلَا يَخْذِلُه’، وَلَا يَكْذِبُه’، ولا يحقره،
Muslim is the brother of a Muslim, he doesn't give him up,
he doesn't betray him, and he doesn't oppress him.
So the way Rasool Allah ﷺ dealt with this situation is that Rasool Ullah made it clear that he disagrees with it.
But he did not punish Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) for it.
But he paid the blood money to the families of the deceased.
And again, the reason why Rasool Ullah paid them is, because the diseased were Muslim, they weren't even Kafir(كافر).
And I tried to clarify this ruling because I think there's a lot of confusion surrounding it.
Unfortunately, some Muslims value the blood of Al-Kuffar(الكفار) more than the blood of the Muslims
and they're willing to hand over their Muslim brothers to the Kuffar(كفار)
and they're willing to fight in fact not only hand over to the Kuffar(كفار) but to fight their Muslim brothers
and this is because the understanding of Wala'a(ولآء) and Bara'a(برآء) in this time is very weak.
This is one aspect of Aqeedah(عقيده) in which the Muslims need to concentrate on
they should know who the loyalty belongs to, and who the Muslim should be free from.
Rasool Allah ﷺ sent Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) to destroy Al-Uzzaa(اَلْاُعُزَّةْ).
Al-Uzzaa(اَلْاُعُزَّةْ) was one of the great gods of the Mushrikeen(مشركين) in those days.
Al-Laat(اَلَّات) wal Uzzaa(اَلْاُعُزَّةْ), Hubal(حُبَل) these are the famous idols that belong to the Mushrikeen(مشركين)
they held them and they consider them to be among their greatest deities.
Rasool Allah ﷺ destroyed the false idols, false gods, the idols surrounding Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه).
And now, Rasool Allah ﷺ wants to destroy Al-Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ), which was outside of Makkah(مكه).
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) went there and the custodians of Al-Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ) ran away.
They didn't fight, they didn't stand to fight.
But in fact the one responsible for Al-Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ) he put the sword around the neck of Al-Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ)
and told Al-Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ) to defend yourself against Khalid(خالد)
and if you don't defend yourself, then you deserve what will happen to you.
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) he came to Al-Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ) and he destroyed it, he destroyed the idol.
When he came back and this narrations is in Al-Bayhaqi(ألْبَيْهَقِيْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: What did he do?
He said: I destroyed Al-Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: You did nothing. Go back!
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) went back.
And now he found a naked woman with her hair was messed up
and she was throwing dirt on herself and she was yelling
Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) put her to the sword and killed her.
And then when he went back to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Rasool Ullah told him: What did you do?
He said: I found a naked woman and I executed her.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: That is Al-Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ), you have killed her.
So, Al-Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ) was some type of Jin(جن) or Shaytan(شيطان)
it was an idol from the outside, but there was a Jin(جن) living inside it
or Shaytan(شيطان) living inside it, and that Shaytan(شيطان) came out, in the form of this naked woman,
so when Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد), executed her that was the end of Al-Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ).
Therefore, there was some superstition attached to Al-Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ)
because there was this, living spirit in it, this Shaytan(شيطان) or Jin(جن).
Probably that played a role in the deceiving of the people.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has said: That there will be no more Uzzaa(اَلْعُزَّةْ) after this day.
Some of the Ihkaam(احكام) in Fath Makkah(فتح مكه),
Rasool Allah ﷺ stayed 18 days and in one narration 19 days.
And during this period he would not fast and he would shorten the Salah(صلاة).
Therefore for example, in the Shafie Mad'hab(شافعي مذهب) and some of the other scholars,
they have taken from this, the ruling that the traveler can shorten the salah(صلاة) and break the fast for 18 days
because of this narration that is in Bukhari(بخاري).
Obviously, there's a difference of opinion.
Some of them say three days and here 18 days.
And then you have even Ibn Taymiya(اِبن تَيْمِيَه) For example, he says;
As long as you are customarily considered to be a traveler you can break your fast, and shorten the Salah(صلاة).
Then there was another incident, and this is the incident of the woman from Bani Makhzoom(بني مخذوم), who was caught stealing.
And Bannu Makhzoom(بنو مخذوم) are prominent family in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), family of Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) among the leaders of the society.
And one of these, and a member of this clan and a noble woman committed the Hadd(حد) of stealing.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered that the punishment of cutting the hand, be applied to her.
Her people and Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) they were very concerned about this.
They're used to the fact that the weak the slaves the people who don't have protection they are punished.
But if you belong to the nobility then there's ways out
we can sort out the deal, find the way out for her.
So they wanted to appeal the punishment.
So, they wanted somebody to speak to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and the person whom they chose was the son of Zaid Bin Harissa(زيد بن حارثه), Usama رضي الله عنه.
They knew that Usama bin Zaid رضي الله عنه is very close to Rasool Ullah.
Rasool Allah ﷺ used to love his father
and Rasool Allah ﷺ loved Usama(اُسَامَه) greatly after his father Zaid Bin Harisa(زيد بن حارثه) was a Shaheed(شهيد) in the Battle of Mu'tah(مَؤتَة).
So because of the strong relationship between Rasool Allah ﷺ and Usama bin Zaid(اُسَامَه بن زيد),
they chose him to speak to Rasool Ullah.
Usama bin Zaid(اُسَامَه بن زيد) agreed and he spoke to Rasool Ullah about it
the face of Rasool Allah changed,
تَلَوَّنَ وَجْهَ رَسول الله صلى الله علي وسلم وَقَالَ: اَتُكَلِّمُنِيْ فِيْ حَدٍ مِنْ حَدُوْدِ الله
You speak to me in a Hadd(حدّ) in a punishment from among the punishments of Allah.
Usama(اُسَامَه) said;
إستغفرلي يا رسول الله
O Rasool Ullah seek my forgiveness
and that day Rasool Allah ﷺ stood and gave a Khut'ba(خطبه) and he said, After praising Allah
فَاِنَّمَا اَهْلَكَ النَّاس قَبْلِكُم اَنَّهُمْ كَانُوْ اِذَا سَرَقَ فِيْهِمْ الشَّرِيْف تَرَكُوْا
وَاِذَا سَرَقَ فِيْهِمْ اَلضَّعِيْفْ اَقَامُوا عَلَيْهَ الْحَدْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: The thing that destroyed people before you,
is that when the noble man among them would steal, they would leave him
and when the weak among them steals.
They would establish the punishment against them.
وَالَّذِى نَفْسٌ محمد بِيَدِه لَوْ اَنَّ فَاطِمَةَ بِنْت محمد سَرَقَتْ لَقَطَعْتُ يَدَهَا
In the name of Whom, my soul is in His Hands
if Fatima(فاطمه) the daughter of Muhammad(محمد) would steal, I would cut her hand.
ثُمَّ اَمَرَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم بِتِلْكَ الْمَرَاَةَ فَقُطِعَتْ يَدُهَا
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered that the hand of that woman be cut
and it says in the Hadith(حديث).
فَحَسُنَتْ تَوْبَتُهَا
She repented after that and she got married.
And Ayesha(عائشه) would say;
فَكَانَتْ تَاْتِيْ بَعْدَ ذَالِكَ فَاَرْفَعَ حَاجَتَهَا اِلَى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
She would visit me after that, if she needs something from Rasool Ullah,
and I would speak to Rasool Allah ﷺ on her behalf.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ is telling us, a law that governs the life of men.
If in a particular society, there's a double standard in applying justice,
where the weak are punished, while the strong are spared,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ will destroy such a society.
Nowadays, brothers and sisters, not only do we have a double standard in applying the law of Allah,
we don't have the law of Allah all together.
So, if Allah would destroy a society and take away the Barakah(بركة) from such as society take away the blessing from it,
just because they have a double standard in applying the law of Allah.
What do you think will happen to us now
because we don't have law of Allah all together.
There's a Hadith(حديث) that says
that applying one Hadd(حدّ), of the Hadood(حدود) of Allah,
Hadd(حدّ) is the criminal law in Islam,
One Hadd(حدّ), applying one Hadd(حدّ) is better than 40 days of rain,
there's more blessing in applying the Hadood(حدود) of Allah then rain for 40 days,
how much Barakah(بركة) are we missing now.
And that is why our life is messed up.
We have a lot of resources, we have wealth, we have such a wide expanse of land, look at how large the Muslim world is.
But there's no Barakah(بركة) in the life,
that is because we don't have the Hadood(حدود) of Allah applied.
And we never tasted the blessing of living under an Islamic system to compare.
See, that's the problem.
But for those who did experience Jahilliyah(جاهلية) and Islam, for example;
There was an Old Woman Who ran into Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه
when he was Khalifah(خليفه), and she told him, how long will this affair last.
I mean, she's talking about the great life that they're living in under Islamic law.
So she asked Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) and told him how long will this last.
Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) told her;
مَسْتَقَامَتْ عَلَيْهَا اَمَّتُكُمْ
As long as your leaders follow it.
As long as the leaders are following Al-Haqq(اَلْحَقْ), you're going to enjoy the blessings.
And then this woman is a Bedouin, she doesn't have knowledge.
So, she told Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), and who are these Aimmah(آئِمَّه),
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) told her; They are the leaders among you.
So, dear brothers and sisters, we should all make it an objective of ours
to try to establish the law of Allahعَزّوجَلّ on Earth.
To try to establish the Islamic system, to try to establish Khilafah(خِلَافَه),
this is a responsibility on every Muslim.
We want to live the blessing of the Islamic system.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: After the conquest of Makkah,
لَا هِجْرَةَ  وَلَكِنْ جِهَادْ وَنِيَّةْ
Before the conquest of Makkah, Hijrah(هجرة) was mandatory
it was one of the most important things Muslim should do.
Anybody who becomes Muslim should make Hijrah(هجرة) from Makkah to Madina, or from any other parts of Arabia.
They are in and they should immigrate to Madina.
After Makkah, People would come to Rasool Allah ﷺ and want to make a Hijrah(هجرة),
Rasool Allah ﷺ would tell them that there's no more Hijrah(هجرة), Khalas(خلاص).
The Hijrah(هجرة) is over and the people who did it, received the Ajr(أجْر).
It's now too late to do Hijrah(هجرة).
But now, you are replaced with Jihad(جهاد),
the thing that takes place of Hijrah(هجرة), and the Ajr(أجْر) of Hijrah(هجرة) is Jihad Fee Sabeel-Lillah(جهاد في سبيل الله).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says in Bukhari(بخاريْ);
لَا هِجْرَةَ  وَلَكِنْ جِهَادْ وَنِيَّةْ وَاِذَا اسْتُنْفِرْتُمْ فَانْفِرُوْا
There is no more Hijrah(هجرة) but Jihad(جهاد) had and intention.
And if you are called to fight then you should respond.
Another man came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and he wanted to give a Baiyah(بَيْعة) to Rasool Allah ﷺ to make Hijrah(هجرة).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said:
اُبَايِعُه’ عَلى الاِسْلام والْجِهَادْ
I will take Baiyah(بَيْعة) from him on Islam and Jihad(جهاد) there's no more Hijrah(هجرة).
So, the rule that applies after the conquest of Makkah is Islam and Jihad Fee Sabeel-Lillah(جهاد في سبيل الله).
And Atta Bin Rabah(عطاء بن رباح) one of the Tabieen(تابعين), he said: I visited Ayesha(عائشه)
and we asked her about Hijrah(هجرة), she said:
لَا هِجْرَةَ الْيَوْم، كَانَ الْمُؤمِنُ يَفِرُّ اَحَدَهُمْ بِدِيْنِهِ اِلَى الله ، عَزُّوجَل، وَاِلَى رَسُوْلِه صلى الله عليه وسلم
مَخَافَةَ اَنْ يُفْتَنَ عَلَيْهِ فَاَمَا الْيَوْم فَقَدْ اَظْهَرَ الله الْاِسْلَامَ ،
فَاْلْمُؤمِنُ يَعْبُدُ رَبَّه’ حَيْثُ يَشَاءْ ، وَلَكِنْ جِهَادٌ وَنِيَّةْ
We asked Ayesha(عائشه) about Hijrah(هجرة) she said;
There's no more Hijrah(هجرة) now.
The believer used to flee with, his religion to Allah and to the Messenger of Allah because of fear of going through Fitnah(فِتْنَه).
They would fear that they would lose their religion
فَاَمَّا الْيَوْم
but today, Allahعَزّوجَلّ has made Islam prevalent.
So the believer can worship Allah wherever, he wants,
but you should fight Jihad Fee Sabeel-Lillah(جهاد في سبيل الله) and you should have the intentions to do so.
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) comments on this and says;
فَلَمْ تَبْقَ الْهِجْرَةْ، الَّلهُمَّ اِلَّا اَنْ يَعْرَضَ حَالٌ يَقْتَضِي الْهِجْرَةَ بِسَبَبْ
مُجَاوَرَةِ اَهْلَ الْحَرْبِ ، وَعَدَمَ الْقُدْرَةَ عَلَى اِظْهَارِ الدِّيْنِ عِنْدَهُمْ ،
فَتَجِبُ الْهِجْرَةَ اِلَى دَارِ الْاِسْلَام، وَهَذَا مِمَّا لَا خِلَافَ عليْهِ بَيْنَ الْعُلَمَاءْ
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) says; So, there's no more Hijrah(هجرة)
except, if there are circumstances that necessitate Hijrah(هجرة),
because of being close to the people of Harb(حرب), the people of war the Kuffar(كفار).
And the inability to show the religion among them,
in this situation, Hijrah(هجرة) becomes mandatory to the land of Islam.
And this is something that is agreed upon among the scholars.
So Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) says; There's more no more Hijrah(هجرة),
except if we run into a situation that is similar to the situation of the Muslims back then,
then Hijrah(هجرة) would be necessary.
And he gives us the clarification of what he means and that is living among the Kuffar(كفار).
If a person is not able to show his religion
if a person can declare his religion publicly,
not only the aspects that are individually practiced,
but he can declare all aspects of Islam in this case Hijrah(هجرة) is not mandatory.
But if a person cannot worship Allah as he should then he must make a Hijrah(هجرة) to the land where he can worship Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Nowadays, we do have clear land of Kuffr(كفر) and clear land of Harb(حرب),
but we do not have a clear land of Islam.
Therefore, the rule that applies now
is that the Muslim should make Hijrah(هجرة) to the place where they can worship Allah the best.
So, it's a relative issue a Muslim,
if he is living in a particular place and he is able to worship Allah as he should then he can remain there
but if he's not, then he should search for the place where there's the least fear on his Deen(دِيْن),
not his Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) his Deen(دِيْن),
and he should make Hijrah(هجرة) to that place.
The final Hadith(حديث) in this section
Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) mentions this Hadith(حديث) as the closing of the chapter of Fath-E-Makkah(فتح مكه).
This Hadith(حديث), it talks about Amr Bin Salamah رضي الله عنه.
Amr Bin Salamah(عَمرُو بن سلمه) was not from Makkah, he belonged to another tribe.
And he describes the situation back then, he says;
Whenever the travelers would travel by, we would ask them about this man referring to Muhammadﷺ,
وَكَانَ يَمُرُّ بِنَا الرُكْبَانْ فَنَسْاَلُهُمْ: مَا لِلنَّاسِ مَاِللنَّاسِ؟ مَا هَذَاالرَّجُلْ؟
We would ask them, about this man.
So the news about Muhammadﷺ was all over Arabia.
And it was the news of the day.
So, people would ask the travelers about any new news about Muhammadﷺ,
that was the major event, the Daw'ah(دعوة) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, it was not an obscure Daw'ah(دعوة).
It was the breaking news for the people all over.
So, Amr Bin Salamah(عَمرُو بن سلمه) said;
We would ask the travelers about this man, and they would say;
فَيَقُوْلُوْنْ: يَزْعَمُ اَنَّ الله اَرْسَلَه’ وَاَوْحَى اِلَيْهِ أو أوحى الله بِكَذَا
So, they would say he claims that Allah has sent him and he's receiving revelation.
And he just received the revelation of this and that.
So these travelers would mentioned some of the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an, they're up to date.
So, they would mention these Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an,
Amr Bin Salamah(عَمرُو بن سلمه) was a child at that time,
and he would hear this dialogue, he would hear this conversation
and he would remember those Ayaat(آيات), he would memorize the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an.
Even though his people were Kuffar(كفار) at that time,
but the people were carrying the Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an around even though they were Kuffar(كفار),
but it was the news for them Rasool Ullah receive this, Rasool Allah ﷺ received that.
فَكُنْتُ اَحْفَظْ ذَالِكَ الْكَلَامْ
I used to memorize those words.
فَكَاَنَّمَا يَقر فِي صَدْرِيْ
As if they would stay inside my breast,
these words, the words of Qur'an would just enter into his breast and stay there.
وَكَانَتِ الْعَرَبْ تَلَوَمُ بِاِسْلَامِهِمْ الْفَتْحْ،
The Arabs were waiting for the conquest, before becoming Muslim.
The Arabs were watching.
They saw two parties in this conflict, Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) on one side and Muhammadﷺ on the other.
And they were waiting to see the result.
That is the situation with many people.
They do not search for the truth, but they look at who is more victorious,
they look at who is more victorious and they follow that victorious party.
وَكَانَتِ الْعَرَبْ تَلَوَمُ بِاِسْلَامِهِمْ الْفَتْحْ،
They were waiting to see who would win.
So, they would say;
فَيَقُوْلُوْنْ: اَتْرَكُوْه’ وَقَوْمَه’، فَاِنَّه’ اِنْ ظَهَرَ عَلَيْهِمْ فَهُوَ نَبِيٌ صَادِقْ
And they would say: If he wins against his people,
they would say: Leave him and his people alone.
If he defeats is people, then he is a Nabi(نَبِي) and he is truthful.
And by the way this is not a correct attitude towards the Daw'ah(دعوة) of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء).
But that is what the people used to say;
I mean we know from the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ, that there are some Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء),
who didn't have any followers, does that make them wrong. No!
I mean, we know the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
on the day of judgment, there will be a Nabi(نَبِي) with 10,
there will be a Nabi(نَبِي) with five,
there will be Nabi(نَبِي) with three,
there would be Nabi(نَبِي) with two, there would be a Nabi(نَبِي) with one follower
and there would be a Nabi(نَبِي) without any followers all together,
that does not make their Da'wah(دعوة), a failure.
It doesn't mean that they know how to do Da'wah(دعوة), No.
because Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
إِنَّكَ لَا تَهْدِي مَنْ أَحْبَبْتَ وَلَٰكِنَّ اللَّهَ يَهْدِي مَنْ يَشَاءُ ۚ
You do not guide whomever you want, but it is Allah, Who guides.
So, the fact that a Nabi(نَبِي) didn't have any followers, that was the Qadar(قَدَر) of Allah,
but he did his job fully in conveying the message.
Anyway, so they waited until Rasool Allah ﷺ defeated his people, Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Now, obviously the ones, who became Muslim earlier,
the ones who accepted Islam earlier,
they searched for the truth and they found it and they accepted Islam.
Their Ajr(أجْر) and their level in the eyes of Allah is much higher than the ones who became Muslim after the victories of Islam (were becoming very clear),
and that's why it says in Qur'an that the ones who fight Jihad Fee Sabeel-Lillah(جهاد في سبيل الله)  and spend before the conquest,
are better and higher in status, than the ones who became Muslim after that, and spent and fought Fee Sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله).
So, there's a difference between becoming Muslim before conquest, and the ones who became Muslim after.
Anyway Amr Bin Salamah رضي الله عنه said that when Rasool Allah ﷺ opened Makkah,
بَادَرَ كُلَّ قَوْمٍ بِاِسْلَامِهِمْ
Every tribe was rushing to become Muslim
وَبَدَرَ اَبِيْ قَوْمِيْ بِاِسْلَامِهِمْ
And my father became Muslim before my people
فَلَمَّا قَدَمْ
When he came back, he said;
جِئْتُكُمْ وَاللهِ مِنْ عِنْدَ نَّبِيْ حَقًا
I came to you in the name of Allah from the Nabi ﷺ,
حقًا
He is truly a Prophet of Allah.
فَقَالْ
he told us, to pray,
صَلُّوْ صَلَاةَ كَذَافِيْ حِيْنَ كَذَا وَصَلُوْ صَلَاةَ كَذَا فِيْ حِيْنَ كَذَا ،
And he told us to pray this Salah(صلاة) at that time and this Salah(صلاة) at that time.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ gave the father of Amr Bin Salamah(عَمرُو بن سلمه) instructions on how to pray.
فَاِذَا حَضَرَتِ الصَّلَاةْ فَلْيُؤَذِّنْ اَحَدكُمْ، وَلَيؤُمَّكُمْ اَكْثَرَكُمْ قُرْآنَا
So when the time of Salah(صلاة) approaches then one of you should make Adhan(آذَان)
and the one, who should be your Imam(اِمَام) is the one who knows the most Qur'an among you.
فَنَظَرُوْ افَلَمْ يَكُنْ اَحَدٌ اَكْثَرْ قُرْآنًا مِّنِّي
So, they searched and they found out that no one knew more Qur'an than me.
لِمَا كُنْتُ اَتَلَقَّى مِنَّ الرُّكْبَاْن
Because of what I learned from the travelers.
فَقَدَّمُوْنِيْ بَيْنَ اَيْدِيْهِمْ
They made me, their Imam(إمام)
وَاَنَا ابْنُ سِتٍ اَوْ سَبْعِ سِنِيْنَ،
And I was six years old or seven years old at the time and he became the Imam(اِمَام).
He knew, the most Qur'an among them.
Amr Bin Salamah(عَمرُو بن سلمه) said;
وَكَانَتْ عَلَيَّ بُرْدَةٌ اِذَا سَجَدْتَ تَقَلَّصَتْ عَنِّيْ
He said: I would lead them in Salah(صلاة) and I was wearing a Burdah(بردة),
a Burdah(بردة) is a square garment and
وَكُنْتُ اِذَا سَجَدْتَ تَقَلَّصَتْ عَنِّيْ
When I would make Sujood(سجود), it was too short, this garment that Amr Bin Salamah(عَمرُو بن سلمه) was wearing was too short,
so when he would go in Sujood(سجود), what happen is this garment would rise and his behind would show.
فَقَالَتِ امْرَاَةْ مِنَ الْحَيّْ اَلَا تُغَطُّوْنَ عَنَّا اسْتَ قارِئِكُمْ
So, one woman stood up and said;
Wouldn't you, cover from us, the butt of your, O reciter.
So, when she did make that statement that embarrassing statement against Amr Bin Salamah(عَمرُو بن سلمه).
In fact, in another narration, it says;
فَكُنْتُ اَؤمَّهُمْ فِيْ بَرْدَةْ مَوْصُوْلَة فيفتق فَكُنْتُ اِذَا سَجَدْتْ خَرَجَتْ إستيْ
He said: I used to lead them in Salah(صلاة) in a Bardah(بردة), in a Thoub(ثوب) that had a big tear from behind.
So, when I would make Sujood(سجود) my butt would stick out of that, tear
and that's why this woman made that statement against him and said,
in front of everyone, this was Ya'ani(يعني) in front of everybody, she said;
Cover from us the butt of your, reciter.
So, Amr Bin Salamah(عَمرُو بن سلمه) said;
فَقَطَعُوْا لِيْ قَمِيْصًا، فَمَا فَرِحْتُ بِشَيْءٍ فَرَحِيْ بِذَالِكَ الْقَمِيْصْ
Now, the Imam(اِمَام) said: They bought for me, a Thoub(ثوب),
now Subhan Allah(سبحان الله) the Imam(اِمَام) has a new Thoub(ثوب)
he's very happy with it. And this is what he said, he said;
And nothing had ever made me so happy as that shirt did.
He was so happy with the new Thoub(ثوب) that, they bought him as an Imam(اِمَام) to cover him up in a Salah(صلاة).
To cover up his Aurah(عَوْرَة).
This is the end of the Ghazwa(غزوة) of Fath Makkah(فتح مكه),
by the way this Hadith(حديث) that I just mentioned, is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًاكَثِيْرَا